<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to Mr. Tho. Edwards the dedication of the letter to our much suspected friend, Mr. T. Edwards, Scavenger Generall, throughout Great-Britaine, New England, and the united Provinces, chiefly Amsterdam, and Munster, and indeed by vertue of some faire pretences, intermeddler in all the states of Christendome, principally there where any thing of the spirit of Christ in the Saints appeares, trenching upon the honour, dignity, and preferment of the old man. The grand reformer, (alias reducer) of the free born sons of God, into the chaines of the their old Babilonish captivity, under the pretence of a Jus Divinum. At his dwelling in Club Courtbetween the Pope and Prelate, a little on this side the fagot in Smithfield, (or if in his monthely Pilgrimage) in the suburbs of Canterbury, at the knowne house of Mistris Gangrena Triplex, where conscience and he (but for a time we hope) shook hands and had each other farewell. Where he was lately discovered by many eye-witnesses: and where you may be sure at any time to meet with him. Published by authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88036</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1721</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E378_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201373</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861896</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861896</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114042</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88036)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114042)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 60:E378[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to Mr. Tho. Edwards the dedication of the letter to our much suspected friend, Mr. T. Edwards, Scavenger Generall, throughout Great-Britaine, New England, and the united Provinces, chiefly Amsterdam, and Munster, and indeed by vertue of some faire pretences, intermeddler in all the states of Christendome, principally there where any thing of the spirit of Christ in the Saints appeares, trenching upon the honour, dignity, and preferment of the old man. The grand reformer, (alias reducer) of the free born sons of God, into the chaines of the their old Babilonish captivity, under the pretence of a Jus Divinum. At his dwelling in Club Courtbetween the Pope and Prelate, a little on this side the fagot in Smithfield, (or if in his monthely Pilgrimage) in the suburbs of Canterbury, at the knowne house of Mistris Gangrena Triplex, where conscience and he (but for a time we hope) shook hands and had each other farewell. Where he was lately discovered by many eye-witnesses: and where you may be sure at any time to meet with him. Published by authority.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Veere, and are to be sold at his shop at the upper-end of the Old Bayley, near New-gate.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Edwards, Thomas. Gangræna.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 25 1646"; the 7 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Edwards, Thomas, 1599-1647. --  Gangræna --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114042:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114042:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A LETTER TO M<hi rend="sup">R</hi>. THO. EDWARDS The Dedication of the Letter</hi> To our much ſuſpected friend, Mr. <hi>T. Edwards,</hi> Scavenger Generall, throughout <hi>Great-Britaine, New-England,</hi> and the united Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, chiefly <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> and indeed by vertue of ſome faire pretences, Intermedler in all the ſtates of Chriſtendome, principally there where any thing of the Spirit of Chriſt in the Saints appeares, trenching upon the Honour, dignity, and preferment of the Old man. The Grand Reformer, <hi>(alias Reducer)</hi> of the free born Sons of God, into the chaines of their old <hi>Babiloniſh</hi> captivity, under the pretence of a <hi>Jus Divinum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At his dwelling in <hi>Club Court,</hi> between the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Prelate,</hi> a little on this ſide the Fagot in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> (or if in his monethly Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage) in the Suburbs of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> at the knowne houſe of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris <hi>Gangrena Triplex,</hi> where Conſcience and he (but for a time we hope) ſhook hands and bad each other farewell. Where he was lately diſcovered by many eye-witneſſes: and where you may be ſure at any time to meet with him.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, Printed for</hi> Tho. Veere, <hi>and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the upper-end of the Old Bayley, near</hi> New-gate. <hi>1647.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:114042:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114042:2"/>
               <head>A LETTER TO M<hi rend="sup">R</hi>. EDWARDS.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir, Worthy Sir, Reverend, Honoured, Grave, Deare Friend, Father, Good Maſter.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee cannot wonder at the loftineſſe of your lookes, nor at the exuberant tumor of your ſpirit, when we finde you ſo wofully beſpatter'd, and courted from every part of the Kingdome, where Sathan we feare hath his throne, with ſo much honour, ſo much worth, ſo much Sir, ſo much reverence, &amp;c. But reverend Sir, if we may be but as bold, and as plaine, as your late correſpondents have been falſe and flattering, give us (or rather take you) the advantage of a ſhort, but ſerious war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>And truly Sir, in the entrance of our diſcourſe, we muſt tell you, our thoughts are extremly divided; your folly hath been ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to all men, that we know not well whether to looke upon you, under the blindneſſe of a deluded brother, or the perverſneſſe of a reſolved enemy; having once (we once believed) received the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth. Wee will put our charity on the Tenters, (as you have put the Covenant,) and if through too much indulgence wee force it beyond the line of its conſcience, wee hope you'l par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don us.</p>
               <p>The over-acting of your zeale, and the ſo violent advance (ſhould we looke no further) hath made us jealous, yea confident, that the fire that hath kindled, and conſumed the ſacrifice was not from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; But Sir, In the ſo deſperate carreer, give us leave ſadly to aske
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114042:3"/>you whence? and whither ſo faſt? Is it ſo long ſince you came out of the houſe of your Bondage, that you have forgotten your anguiſh, and your ſorrow there, and will needs be poſting backe againe? was their yoke ſo eaſie, and their burthen ſo light, that you can ſo freely bow-down your necke and your backe, and rejoyce in your approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſlavery? Is your late, and your preſent mercy (your halfe hours ſilence in heaven) ſo uncouth, and unſavoury, that nothing but the Onions and Garlick of <hi>Egypt</hi> will ſatisfie the luſtings of your ſoule? Is the affliction of <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſo ſmal in your eie, that like <hi>Hammon</hi> all your enjoyments are nothing; while <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſits in the gate of the King, and will not bow the knee? and nothing elſe ſhall cool the tip of your tongue, but the irons, and fetters, the whips and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the confiſcation, the blood, the death, and the ruine of the Saints? God ſhall ſmite thee thou whited wall, that thus in the pride of thy heart, flyeſt in his face, and ſtrikeſt at the very apple of his eye. If divine juſtice ſhall ſuffer thee without checke or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule to run on for a time, adding Iniquity to Iniquity, and treaſuring wrath againſt the day of wrath: confident we are, when thy ſoule ſhall ſit upon thy trembling lips, and thy two laſt years pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, and perſecutions, (wherein thou ſo much glorieſt) ſhall be ſet in order before thee, and thy conſcience awakened, to behold thy guilt; thou wilt appeare a ſpectacle, of as much horror and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement as ever the Sun beheld; In the meane time, come forth and appear in your colours, and let the world ſee whither you have acted the part of a Chriſtian, or of a Jew; of an Engliſh man, or a Turk; of a Saint or of ſomwhat worſe: lay aſide the ſquint eyed by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing reſpects of this adulterous Generation, and let conſcience ſpeake; once in your dayes (if you can) tell truth; who (under God) have been the pillars and onely ſupporters of a reeling tottering State? At the price of whoſe bloud for ſome yeares have you eaten your bread in peace, and injoyed every thing that is ſweet and pleaſant? who hath ſtept between death and you, and for you have offered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo gallantly in the high places of the field? yet once againe, (if conſcience will be but true) whom hath God honoured (as with his power, ſo) with his ſpirit in an exellent meaſure? This we know is the rocke of offence. And yet here will the aſſe whom you ride, riſe up and unplead the blindneſſe of his maſter. Take the common people that have neither God nor goodneſſe, but meerly acted by you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114042:3"/>and your party, (ſetting aſide the Malignants and the fore ſtall'd) and ſcarce any but will acknowledge a ſpirit of Goſpell-ſweetneſſe, and that of a truth God is in thoſe people. And Sir, are theſe the onely objects of your ſcorne and contempt, and the rage of your retinue, that rude and Godleſſe Generation? Are theſe to be trampled under foot, and not fit to live in a Kingdome? In whoſe faces no dirt nor dung is too filthy to be throwne. Had wee a deſire to gratifie that grand accuſer, to publiſh through <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askelon,</hi> and to make the uncircumciſed to Glory in your ſhame; we could preſent the world with farre more, and more faire teſtimonies of the notorious villanies (not in matters of judgement (which is your charge) for therein their groſſe Egyptian ignorance takes care) but in matters of fact) among the reſt, we could tell the world and you a truer ſtory of the late Prankes of Mr, &amp;c. (whoſe name you know, but we will ſpare) of his late ſupplanting the Merchant, and getting his eſpouſed Miſtris with childe (which act, with its circumſtancies we finde not in all your gangrene paralleld) and of his publique penance and acceptation; we could give you in another of the ſame name, order and crime, in a neighbour-Pariſh in <hi>London,</hi> and both (we muſt tell you) as popular, as Reverend, as Orthodox, and as Covenant-engaged as your ſelfe; we could bring in a bed-roll of thoſe halting ſonnes of <hi>Eli,</hi> but we profeſſe it not our trade, and we will not intrench upon yours.</p>
               <p>Wee could trace you through the unhallowed paths of your Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie, and your ungodly gangrenes, (firſt, ſecond, and third,) and throw many a lye in your face. That buſineſſe of Mr. <hi>Bachelors,</hi> wherein (though you brand him in your booke) you could not deny to his face, but acknowledged him, to be cleare in fundamentals, (wherein was his charge) and that he was not the man you took him for. This you confeſt, yet (perhaps out of purpoſe to forſweare, when time may ſerve) you refuſed to diſcourſe before his friend, though he offered you the liberty of yours.</p>
               <p>Wee would aske you what godly Miniſter, or Gentleman, or Friend that was, that told you that ungodly lye of that godly Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, who you ſay, was thrown out of the Army, becauſe a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Presbyterian, when hundreds can teſtifie, he was caſheerd by a Councell of warre, for drunkenneſſe, and ſwearing God dam-mee, &amp;c. wee could with a little paines (but leſſe pleaſure) dig up thoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114042:4"/>filthy dunghils, and ſend home your baſtards to their proper parents. Truly Sir, our wonder is the leſſe that your births are ſo Monſtrous, when we finde the contributions have been ſo adulterous. <hi>Flectere ſi nequeas ſuperos Acheronta movebis.</hi> To carry on the deſigne you doe well to uſher in a forraigne force: The Netherlands have done you good ſervice: The <hi>Munſter</hi> Brigade, bearing the Van, hath made the moſt deſperate aſſault, and yet through a narrow watch, and diligent inſpection, the guſt thereof is broken; the Leader on, and Charger, being found a ſtranger, is not an enemy. However Sir, be not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged (if you dare) the cauſe is ſtill the ſame (as bad as ever) rally once more, and bring in againe (you are good at that) your weather-beaten forces; give not up at the firſt repulſe, you know whom for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune doth uſually favour. Send againe to the Reformed Churches, and ſee if any more aid may be expected thence. Search <hi>Amsterdam</hi> once more, (if you pleaſe with candles) or any other corner of the world (ſo farre as the Covenant by you ſo wyar-drawn will reach) where ever you can heare of a Saint, and let ſomething be done to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſo honourable a worke. Go on Sir in this gallant ſervice, if conſcience or prudence will give you leave, and hug the world as the world ſeemes to hug you, untill their turne be ſerved, and tell us then (for then you will ſpeak truth if ever) whether's more tollerable, Nick-nam'd Hereſie, or Malignant-Prelacy, that ſeven headed, ten horned beaſt, which for a little time hath withdrawn, and changing his form in ſuch furious perſons as you are, appears again, acted dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly by the ſame ſpirit, ſpeaking great things againſt God and his Saints, and differing onely in the Number of his name.</p>
               <p>Sir, you with your Gangrene have been waighed, and are found too light, and verily your expected Kingdome is departing; while you are beating your fellow ſervants, and your Sect triumphing over us and ours, a third hath ſurpriſed both, and all are poſting into capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity againe: ſhift for your ſelfe and ſelves as well as yee can, and in your brick and no ſtraw, remember who were once the Taskmaſters. Wee do believe the Thumbs and Toes of <hi>Adonibezecke,</hi> will one day lye before you. For our parts we know whom we have believed, and (our feet being ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpell) we doubt not but we ſhal be able to tread upon the Lyon &amp; the Adder, &amp; to play upon the hole of the Aſpe. Wee know that an Idoll is nothing in the world, neither are we careful to fall down before <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114042:4"/>his God, though the furnace be ſeven times hotter then ordinary; coſt us what it will, Truth we know will pay its owne charges: Every inſtitution and truth of God (though ſlanderouſly reported) we ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and imbrace; but for that golden calfe, that <hi>nec jus humanum, nec divinum, neque ſacrum, nec politicum, neque ſanum, nec Chriſtianum,</hi> that ſelfe contradicting, groundleſſe, lifeleſſe, ſpiritleſſe Image of jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, whoſe externall brightneſſe is excellent, and the forme thereof very terrible, the head of gold, the breaſt and armes of ſilver, the belly and thighs of braſſe, the legs of iron, the feet (or foundation) part of iron, and part of clay; this we have beheld, and beholding ſhall expect, untill that little ſtone cut out of the mountaine without hands ſhall ſmite head and foot, and over-turning the foundation thereof it ſelfe ſhall fill the world; we are thoroughly aſſured that not by might, nor by power, but by the ſpirit of the Lord, (which is both might and power) which you have ſo deſperately denyed, if not deſpited) ſhall Anti-Chriſt be unvailed, and by the ſame ſpirit of burning ſhall every thing that is Anti-Chriſtian be deſtroyed; what ſay you Sir, have you not faith enough to believe this? know you (not who ſaith the weapons of our warfare are not carnall (why then as men diſtracted cry yee out ſo loud for Magiſteriall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall force?) but mighty through God, to the pulling downe of <hi>STRONG HOLDS,</hi> caſting down <hi>IMAGINATIONS</hi> and <hi>EVERY HIGH THING</hi> that exalteth it ſelfe againſt the knowledge of God; and bringing into captivity <hi>EVERY HIGH THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHT</hi> (or <hi>OPINION</hi>) to the <hi>OBE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIENCE</hi> of <hi>CHRIST.</hi> Dare you not truſt God on his word? but deny the Scripture, not in the letter onely, but in the ſpirit of it alſo? who is the Sectary and the Hereticke now Sir? A ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall man would judge that the <hi>SHIELD</hi> of <hi>FAITH,</hi> the <hi>SWORD</hi> of the <hi>SPIRIT,</hi> the <hi>GIRDLE</hi> of <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH,</hi> &amp;c. (whoſe very anoyntment and ordination is to that very office) might do as gallant execution in the hand of the ſpirituall champion (a Miniſter of the Goſpell) and make as ſucceſſefull an advance upon ſpirituall wickedneſſes in high places (as Errours and Hereſies are) as all the unſutable, Incongruous, unapoynted proviſion of your car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Artillery; yee war indeed, but 'tis after the fleſh, and no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your conqueſt is no more, for the ſpirit of the Lord we feare is departed from yee.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114042:5"/>
               <p>You ſtand quarrelling away your time, and waſting your little ſtrength, in a company of frothy, ulcerous Pamphlets; vilifying the upright, and ſlandering the innocent, wholly neglecting your work, which (you would make men believe) is the Miniſtry of Chriſt, which you indeed either wholly wave, or groſſely pervert; and to backe your unſound interpretations, produce the authority of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of (forſooth) Fathers of the Church, as <hi>Bernard,</hi> &amp;c. men though lights in their darke Generation, and in many things ſound in the faith, yet in others as palpably hereticall, as any of your damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sectaries, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſuffrage of Saints departed, prayers for the dead, the reall preſence in the conſecrated Hoſts, &amp;c. Sir, ſave your relfe this labour of ſearching theſe corrupt records, wee pin not our faith on the ſleeves of any, though never ſo ancient, or Authenticke with you. Your ſuborning of witneſſes makes us ſuſpect the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are not your friends; we profeſſe, (except your braines be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated, or your naturall reaſon be intranc'd (or which is worſe then both) you make it your deſigne with Sophiſtry to cheat your proſelites) wee know not what to thinke of your impertinent, ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, unſchollar-like argumentations, <hi>a baculo ad angulum;</hi> from the Jew to the Gentile, from the law to the Goſpell, from the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to the Magiſtrate, &amp;c. Tell us not Sir of a ſpecious ordination any farther then you can atteſt its divinity by the concomitancy of the ſpirit; wee ſhall elſe looke upon it as a meanes to delude the ſimple. Tell us not (as your predeceſſors did) of order and decency in the Church: yours (you know) differs much from theirs, (as <hi>NEW LORDS</hi> uſe to make <hi>NEW LAWES</hi>) and why may not wee (without theſe complainings to Authority) a little diſſent from you; if you and men of like ſpirit will conſtitute more then any (without the helpe of ſpecticles) can ſee to be canonicall, Mickle gude may they doe yee; for our part, though our orders received not their forme from your mould, yet we are confident the Apoſtle ſpeaks nothing but truth, when he ſaid, God is not the Author of confuſion, but of peace (or order) as in all <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCHES</hi> of the <hi>SAINTS,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33.</p>
               <p>Let's not have ſuch brutiſh dealing Sir, as to be put into Beares skins, and then your canibals to be let looſe upon us; yee idle and loyter, and feed upon the fat of the flocke, and ſay, to morrow ſhall be as this day and much more abundant; your Tithes and other Incomes your three or foure or five hundred pounds <hi>per annum</hi> take
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114042:5"/>up your time and yee neglect the worke, in the meane time tares are ſowne, and errors and hereſies come up thicke and three-fold; and then with open mouth yee cry out, Oh theſe accurſed <hi>Julians,</hi> Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, theſe damnable Antinomians, Anabaptiſts, Independents, &amp;c. that will ruine all (The world is turned Biſhop again to the very life; <hi>Bonner</hi> himſelfe is riſen from the dead, and nothing will doe but the death of diſſentors, what ſay you (Sir) to the Sacrament of the Altar, fall downe to the Idoll, or bring in the halter) Sir, once more in good earneſt take home your ugly brats; and yee that upon your beds of eaſe have gotten ſuch Monſters, beſtow then as yee pleaſe: for our part we doe profeſſe they are none of ours, neither do we at all plead for their tolleration. Wee abhor the remembrance of them, and ſhall as freely contribute to their deſtruction as any; Only Sir, for the ordinance of Magiſtracy, we would not engage them in a practice ſo diſhonourable, and deſtructive, but with (Mr. <hi>Marſhall</hi>) ſhall deſire them to peruſe their Commiſſion, and act accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
               <p>Sir, Were you a meſſenger of Chriſt, your worke would be to go and preach, and hold forth the everlaſting Goſpell, which alone is the Arme of God to ſalvation, you would more cry up the ſword of God, then of <hi>Gideon;</hi> you would ſee more cogent, convincing au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to ſubdue the heart, by one Evangelicall <hi>Scriptum est,</hi> then a thouſand politicall <hi>fiat juſtitia's,</hi> or all the Arbitrary, bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, canonicall, <hi>Ipſe dixis's,</hi> in the world.</p>
               <p>Fill not the world with clamors of Schiſmatickes, and Hereticall ſeducers; you have an engine in your hand, and that of God, which if weilded, as ordered, will fetch backe the wandring; yea, ſeduce the ſeducers themſelves. However Sir, though thouſands ſhould fall at your right hand (I meane to errors) and ten thouſand at your left, yet know that every one that the father hath given to the ſon, is as a ſtarre in his owne right hand, and none ſhall be able to plucke him thence: Many muſt and ſhall back-ſlide, that thoſe that are ſound might be approved; and this Sir, is our everlaſting rocke, that in the moſt deſperate apoſtacy, and falling away) the foundation of the Lord ſtandeth ſure, having this <hi>SEALE</hi> [the Lord knowes who are his.]</p>
               <p>You have been bold Sir, with the truth and us; give us leave in the behalfe of the truth to be bold with you, 2nd plainly to tell you, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114042:6"/>your Clergicall Intereſts have broke the back of Chriſtendome, and the myſtery of Iniquity begins to appeare; your fathers have eaten (ſweet) ſower Grapes, and your childrens teeth are ſet on edge; your Patent yee received from them, and they from Antichriſt (as his laſt will and teſtament) by vertue whereof, the trade muſt wholy run through your hands; yee muſt kill and ſlay without controule, and wound at your pleaſures, and none muſt binde up the broken but yee. The way to Heaven yee tell men is by the gate of Hell, and more then halfe damned they muſt be, ere they muſt thinke of being ſaved; and who but yee (in the diſpaire of poor creatures) ordained to ſpeak peace. And if any other (whom God hath better gifted for the worke of the Miniſtry then with a black coat, an univerſity dialect, and the externall advantage of Arts and Sciences) ſhall preſume to lay hands on your arke, why preſently he uſurpes the Prieſtly office (<hi>alias</hi> the Prelaticall preferment) And muſt immediately be curſed with Bell, Booke and Candle. Theſe Sir, are the ſhrines whereby your <hi>Diana</hi> have been ſo long ſupported. This vault of darkneſſe, this helliſh conſpiracy, by a beam of the morning ſtarre hath been diſcovered, which makes the Heathen rage, and which we hope will be found to be the laſt proppe of Antichriſt, <hi>veniente Rege,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And in concluſion, as a monumentall relique of your unſpeakable atcheivements in the fundament of Learning, (ſetting aſide thoſe ſublime Encomiums of a godly friend, a Godly Miniſter, &amp;c. ſent from ſuch and ſuch a place in the Country, and your ſelfe-flattering dreames of a ſecond <hi>Luther, cum multis aliis ridiculoſis</hi>) were is not to broad a diſparagement to our mother univerſity, we could ſend you with your hornbook at your backe, to take your degree among the pupils in Pauls for helpe to reconcile the abſurd contradiction of a believing Atheiſt. Turne to Page the (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>) of your laſt Gangrene, and bluſh not if you can) wee know not what were the methods of your Maſters Indulgence, but the Tithe of this errour in our Schoole had been ſix laſhes at leaſt: But Sir, this and twenty ſuch ſcapes, wee'l winck at; wee'l accept of the will for the deed, and ballance the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt with your zeale, your loyalty, and your faithfulneſſe to the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But Sir, In good earneſt let's have more ſence and leſſe volumes, fewer tales and more truths, ſmaller bookes and bigger Arguments. (Theſe bum-baſte editions tyre all, but ſatisfie none) Reaſons are ſold by weight, and not by tale. No marvell you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114042:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>catch no more birds (except now and then a woodcocke or two) your baite is ſo ſlight and chaffey; your Induſtrious <hi>SMITH</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell you ſo, by that time he hath caſt up his cards, and brought in a to tall accompt, a ruffe draught whereof you may take at preſent, as followeth. <hi>Imprimis,</hi> given to the Honourable Houſe of Commons, out of hopes to finde favour there, ſo many books. <hi>Item.</hi> given to your Reverend ſelf, for your reverend Copy ſo many. <hi>It.</hi> given to a School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy to correct your falſe Latine, and other amendments 40 <hi>s.</hi> in dry money (too much by 39 in ſo dry a bargaine.) <hi>It.</hi> given to the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an for helping you to the Originals, and filling up the Hebrew blanks, 59 <hi>s.</hi> and three groats, (Oh the Lamentation of a bad market) <hi>It.</hi> ſould at ſeverall times with much adoe and little profit, ſo many: <hi>It.</hi> ſent to the Reformed Churches to ſhew them the variety of our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries, and your valiant encountrings, ſo many. <hi>It.</hi> given away to friends to make a party, who have taken the Covenant to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to us till death, ſo many. <hi>It.</hi> ſo many let out at Livery at pence a peece, but finding no ſatisfaction returned them, ſpoiled, ſo many. <hi>It.</hi> ſo many ſold for little or nothing, to the Exchange, to Grocers, Cooks, &amp;c. <hi>It.</hi> truſted in the hands of Huckſters, but not yet retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, (nor we believe ever will) being hardly worth bringing backe ſo many. <hi>It.</hi> ſo many ſtolne for want of care, and looking after, being pind on the wall for a Lure. <hi>It.</hi> ſo many ſequeſtred for my owne proper uſe, in my ſtudy behind the doore (<hi>alias</hi> the houſe of office) and for my ſervants ſo many. <hi>It.</hi> tranſported for France, that hot inflaming clymate, the leaves there of (as you ſaid) being very ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign for the healing of the Nations. And laſtly, (to ballance the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts with the bakers dozen) lying ſtill in my hands, and are like there to lye ſo many hundreds; Come along cuſtomers if you lacke any. That this is a true and perfect accompt, I have hereunto ſet my hand, <hi>R.S.</hi> Yet that you may not take all upon bare report (as hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you have done) behold the powerful convincing pen of our Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan Surveyer, who is able to give you as good an accompt in this caſe as hee did of the Tithe in Chriſt-Chuch.</p>
               <p>Brother <hi>Tom,</hi> this Account though ſtrange and unexpected, yet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the requeſt and credit of our well-beloved Truſtee R. S. I have peruſed, and cannot but judge Orthodox; and though for the honour of our Cauſe <hi>(Conſider atis conſiderandis) nullo modo Imprimatur,</hi> yet for the incouragement of that ſpeaking <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> and all ſuch wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114042:7"/>undertakers, <hi>Ambobus manibus, Iterum Iteru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> que approbatur, J. C.</hi> — And now Sir, having preſented you with a ſmall Map of your unworthy dealing, your <hi>Rabſhakah</hi>-ralings, your accurſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſings, your undue, untrue, unchriſtian ſlanderings of your Brethren, We ſhall ſpread the ſame in the preſence of the Lord, and leave you to the Rebnkes of him, who hath and will rebuke Kings and Kingdoms for his anointeds ſake. Onely (if yet there may be hope) apply to thy Gangrened ſtate, that corroding plaiſter, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6. And ſo we bid thee farewell. From our Pallace in our priſon, from our Harbour in our ſtorme, from our ſtrong City, in our wayfairing ſtate, from our all in all in our nothing at all, wherein no ſtranger ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle, nor any theef ſhall break through to ſpoile us of our ſweet repoſe.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Primo Febr.</hi> 1646.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Copy of the Letter to the Gentlewoman, in which this Letter to <hi>Mr. Edwards</hi> was incloſed.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Mistris,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe incloſed is the Copy of a Letter ſent and delivered to the hand of Mr. Tho. Edwards, the famous forger of theſe latter dayes, whom when you ſee commend us to him (for the world and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience well know, how fouly we have been belied) and tell him the Seſſion is haſting wherein our plea will impartially be heard and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold reparations awarded us for our manifold tribulations, till when the Anchor of our Hope being entred into that within the Vaile, we ſhall bee able to paſſe the ſtreights of this wicked world, and to ride out the rugged wafts of a Rocky Sea:</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
